A Guide to the Daniel Family Papers, 1794-1898
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Daniel Family Papers, 1794-1898
The Library of Virginia
23952
109 leaves, negative photostats
Daniel Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying, March 1953, by Mrs. Robert Daniel of Brandon, Virginia, through Samuel M. Bemiss, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Edmund Randolph (1753-1813) attended the College of William and Mary from 1770 to 1771 and studied law. He served in the Fifth Virginia Convention which adopted the state's first constitution. Randolph served as Virginia's Attorney-General from 1776 to 1786 and was elected to Congress, serving there in 1779 and 1781-1782. Randolph was elected governor of Virginia in 1786 and served until 1788. Randolph also attended the Federal Constitutional Convention in 1787 and the state ratifying convention in 1788. Washington appointed Randolph United States Attorney-General in 1790 and Secretary of State in 1794, resigning in 1795. Randolph spent the rest of his life as a lawyer and author. He married Elizabeth Carter Nicholas (1753-1810) 29 August 1776, and they had 4 children. His daughter Lucy Nelson Randolph (1788-1847) married Peter Vivian Daniel (1784-1860) of Stafford County, Virginia, 20 April 1810. He studied law under Randolph. He represented Stafford County in the House of Delegates from 1809 to 1812, when he was appointed to the Council of State. As a member of the Council, Daniel served as lieutenant governor of Virginia. He was appointed to the United States Supreme Court in 1840. Peter V. and Lucy Daniel had 3 children, including Peter V. Daniel, Jr. (1818-1889) who was a lawyer and a civil engineer. He was president of the Richmond and Petersburg Railroad from 1843 to 1860, and of the Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad from 1860 to 1873. Daniel, Jr., married Mary Robertson (1815-1890) 1 December 1846, and they had 2 children. Daniel, Sr., married Elizabeth Harris (d. 1857) and they had 2 children.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1794-1898, of the Daniel family of Stafford County and Richmond, Virginia, consisting of letters, 1794-1813, from Edmund Randolph (1753-1813) concerning American relations with Spain, France, and Great Britain, politics, William Short's (1759-1849) performance as minister to Spain, Thomas Pinckney's (1750-1828) appointment as a commissioner to Spain, Jay's Treaty, Randolph's resignation as Secretary of State, and family and personal matters; letters, 1811-1861, of the Daniel family concerning personal and family matters, the Civil War, and election of the Confederate Congress; deeds, 1807-1846, for property in Stafford County; notes, 1811-1878 and no date, on religion, Page family genealogy, insurance, Thomas Nelson (1738-1789), and Rochester and Canandaigua Lakes, New York; tombstone inscriptions, copied 1898, of the Burwell, Mann, and Page families of Gloucester County, Virginia; law license, 10 March 1843, for Peter V. Daniel, Jr. (1818-1889); and roster of the Union Volunteer Cavalry of Richmond, ca. 1812-1815.
Contents List
- Letter, 16 March 1794, from Secretary of State Edmund Randolph (1753-1813) to the American minister to Spain William Short (1759-1849) concerning Edmond Genet (1763-1834), and relations with Spain, Great Britain, and France.
- Letter, 18 August 1794, from Randolph to Short concerning U.S. foreign policy and U.S. politics.
- Letter, 9 November 1794, from Randolph to Short concerning relations with Spain and Short's performance as minister
- Letter, 25 December 1795, from Randolph to Thomas Pinckney (1750-1828) of South Carolina appointing Pinckney to go to Spain to work out an agreement over disputes between the U.S. and Spain.
- Letter, 21 July 1795, from Randolph to Short informing Short of the efforts to ratify Jay's Treaty with Great Britain.
- Letter, 26 November 1797, from Randolph to his son Peyton Randolph (1784-1828) containing greetings and family news.
- Letter, 3 February 1805, from Randolph to his daughter Lucy Nelson Randolph (1788-1847) telling her he misses her.
- Deed, 14 September 1807, for a tract of land in Stafford County, Virginia, from Travers Daniel (1741-1824) to his son Peter Vivian Daniel (1784-1860), both of Stafford County.
- "Notes for letters on religion to my children," 28 June 1811, by Lucy Nelson Randolph Daniel.
- Letter, 7 August 1811, from Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel containing her thoughts on their religious and personal life.
- Letter, 11 June 1812, from Randolph to an unidentified correspondent in Baltimore, Maryland, about the difficulties of arranging a meeting between them.
- Letter, 12 April 1821, from Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel containing personal news.
- Letter, 30 April 1821, from Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel discussing personal and family news.
- Letter, 2 July 1821, from Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel sending personal and family news.
- Letter, 10 August 1831, from Lucy Daniel to Edwin H. Randolph (1812-1833) of Amelia County, Virginia, asking Randolph to come for a visit to Richmond.
- Letter, 8 June 1833, from Peter V. Daniel, Jr. (1818-1889), to Edwin H. Randolph sending personal and family news.
- Letter, October 1839, from Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel, Sr., concerning the education of Peter V. Daniel, Jr., and containing family news.
- Genealogical notes, 26 March 1842, of the Page family of Gloucester County, Virginia.
- License, 10 March 1843, for Peter V. Daniel, Jr., to practice law in the courts of Virginia.
- Deed, 24 February 1846, for 500 acres in Stafford County from Peter V. Daniel, Sr., and Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel, Jr., all of Richmond, Virginia.
- Letter, 20 February 1847, from Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel concerning the marriage of their son and personal news.
- Letter, 4 October 1861, from Peter V. Daniel, Jr., to an unknown correspondent concerning railroad business, news of the Civil War, and an election for the Confederate Congress.
- Note, 14 October 1878, from Herbert A. Claiborne to Peter V. Daniel, Jr., concerning insurance bought in 1803 on the home built by his grandfather Edmund Randolph.
- Transcriptions, 21 August 1898, of tombstone inscriptions, 1658-1721, of the Burwell family of Gloucester County, copied by H. W. Daniel.
- Transcriptions, 21 August 1898, of tombstone inscriptions, 1693-1704, of the Page and Mann families of Gloucester County copied by H. W. Daniel.
- Letter, 25 August [1795], from Edmund Randolph in New York, New York, to his wife Elizabeth Carter Nicholas Randolph (1753-1810) concerning politics and his resignation as Secretary of State.
- Letter, no date, from Lucy Daniel to Peter V. Daniel containing news of family and friends (incomplete).
- "Thoughts on the the situation of the late General Nelson's affairs," no date, by Edmund Randolph.
- Roster of the members of the Union Volunteer Cavalry of Richmond, ca. 1812-1815.
- Note, no date, on Rochester Lake and Canandaigua Lake in New York by Fanny Kemble (1809-1893).
- Transcriptions, no date, of tombstone inscriptions, 1707-1764, for the Page family of Gloucester County.